北野武电影工作室
站住！
Hey, man, stop!
哎，站住！
老板，给兄弟们俩钱借点花花吧
Mister, we want your money.
快些！
Hurry
利索点！
Hurry up!
快些！
Do it now!
喂！
No!
[晋剧《断桥》]
青儿妹妹莫动手
A TOUCH OF SIN
官人呀~~~你狠心把我丢
自那日儿~~~
在西湖得识郎面
又谁知好姻缘呀~~~
变成孽缘端阳节~~~
师傅，乌金山怎么走嘀？
What is the path to the Black Gold Mountain?
就这儿
You're on it.
307呢？
- Rodovia 307?
就这儿
- Keep going that way.
[圣母圣婴画像和毛塑像]
[糖尿病人注射用的胰岛素笔]
大海
Dahai.
[友情客串~韩三明：《三峡好人》主演]
外面谁的三轮车 ?
Whose bike is that out there?
不知道谁的
- I do not know.
嗳，咋啦？
- Do not know!
来，大海，坐
Sit down, Dahai.
放在那儿两天了，我们也不知道谁的
It's been standing there for two days. No idea whose it is.
没人要，我弄到街上卖了去
If nobody claims her, I'll sell it.
㖿
那村长的奥迪A6放在他家门口，也没人开
So if the Audi A6 the village chief was parked ...
你也卖了吧?
outside his house, would you sell that, too?
你也卖了
What do you think?
他那奥迪A6是全村人人有份
That A6 belongs to everyone here in the village.
要不是把集体煤矿转给私人，他有鸟买啊？
He sold the state the coal mine for the money to buy that fancy car.
怪不得看着有点眼熟呢
So that's why I found the car so familiar.
那贼亮贼亮的车轱辘，原来是我的啊
Those shiny new wheels are actually mine.
嗯，有觉悟
You caught the spirit.
大海
Dahai.
真是把你生的有点晚了
It's a shame you were not born ...
要是生在战争年代
for example, before the war.
你，可要混个开国大将来当当咯
Surely you would have made the rank of General.
唉，反正别逼哥
We'll see what happens
等俺到了北京找到中纪委
when I make the complaint to Beijing.
让村长和那焦老板，一起去二监拉沙子去
The boss and the new boss, Jiao will be sent to jail.
就怕你还没到了太原
Before even reaching Tainan ...
就让村长给把你给修扁了
the boss's men will bribe you.
哎！老子这几年法律不是白学的
Why do you think I studied law?
村长一条低价转卖集体资产
Boss sold a collective property,  which he could not do.
行贿受贿，出卖国家资源
The bastard accepted bribes.
老子让他坐二十年牢！
Surely he'll get 20 years.
还有你们焦老板，不是牛屄吗？不是有钱吗？
As for the boss, Jiao Shengli, he's also involved in that, is he not?
我告他焦化厂污染环境，隐瞒矿难
He will be charged with theft and covering up accidents in the mine.
让他所有的企业都关了门，信么？
All this serves to close the mine.
信么？
Believe you me. Believe it.
哼
Hmmm
当时的煤矿没承包给你
If the coal mine had been  yours ...
要是承包给你，你还不是一样样的？
you also would have acted just like him. Just like him.
哎，不一定啊
Sure.
那焦老板家里那辆玛莎拉蒂在院儿停着
Jiao's Maserati is parked in the courtyard.
也没人开
He never drives it.
大海，干脆你开出去卖了，请大伙儿喝酒！
If you sell it, you can buy a drink for everyone.
噫呵，二奶的车，老子不要！
I don't want his dam car.
三明，火车票买了没有？
Sanming. Bought a train ticket?
买好了
Yes, I bought one.
去哪儿啊？
For what?
腊月二十三到湖北接媳妇回来
See my wife on the New Year.
哟，好浪漫哦
How romantic!
哎，检查了，检查了，都到外头
The police are here.
等一会再吃，嗳，快快快，伙计
Police. Come on, stop eating. Stop eating.
检查了
Inspectors.
老宋，外地介都在了吧？
All here are migrant workers?
在了，咋啦？
Yes. What's the problem?
哎，十八湾出了人命嘹，检查外地介了
A crime in Shibawan. The migrants need to be interrogated.
你招呼一下，都让他们过来
Everyone out there.
行
Alright.
利索些，快去
Quickly.
村长！
Chief.
哎，村长！
Village chief.
乌金山煤矿承包给胜利的时候
when you sold the coal mine you promised ...
说好了每年都有分红
profit sharing. So where's our part?
嗳，悄悄嘀吧
I said that in a private conversation.
我没有时间跟你说
I don't have time for this right now.
嗳，你不跟我说，到时候跟中纪委的人说
Right. So explain this to the disciplinary committee.
你小子呀
商量也不会选时候
You picked the wrong time to get into a fight.
一辈子也气不到塞个东西！
Could end up getting killed.
噗！
老宋呢？
You do not want to discuss it?
就你话多！
You talk too much.
来，重庆的出来
Very well. These are from Chongqing.
站那边去呀
Stay there.
下一个
Next.
511、225、1971、0323、[下一个] 5090，完毕
到那边去呀。来，下一个
511、225、1971……
哎！跑了！
He's running.
站住！
站住！别跑！
驾、驾、驾……
牲口！
Fucking animal!
驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾……
驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾……
[背景音：邵氏经典影片《独臂刀》]
好
现在大家都是本来面目
用不着装着玩咯
这下我赔你两条胳膊……
可惜你这小子自己只有一条
就拿命来赔了！
亮出你的齐家金刀，动手吧！
[兵器碰击声、笔划信纸声]
唉！
[兵器撞击声]
大海，做啥呢？
What's happening, Dahai?
嗳，给中纪委写告状信
I am writing to the disciplinary committee ...
告狗日的村长，还有焦胜利
to file a complaint against the boss and Jiao Shengli.
姑娘，寄挂号信
Girl. A registered letter.
寄哪儿呐？
Where to?
北京、中南海、中纪委
Beijing. Zhongnanhal. The committee.
具体的地址和邮编？
I need the full address.
北京中南海啊！
Zhongnanhai, Beijing.
啧！不行，得有具体的地址！
That's not enough. I need the whole address.
妳少废话！
What?
北京谁不知道中南海啊？！
Everyone knows Zhongnanhai.
不行！
But it's not enough.
姑娘，妳跟村长是一伙儿的吧？
Girl, are you on the boss's side?
他贪污的钱妳花啦？
Is he paying you off?
要不，妳是焦老板的二奶？
Or are you fucking Jiao?
他给妳买车买房子啦？
Did he buy you a car?
你有病吧？你！走！
Are you crazy? Go away!
他妈的妳跟他是一伙儿的吧？！
You two must be together in this.
走！
Out.
没天理了！
There is no justice!
没天理了！！
没天理了！！！
There is no justice!
该走的都走了！出发啦！快点！
Hurry!
All aboard! We are starting! Let's go!
大海！大海！走！ 上来！
Dahai! Dahai! Come on!
快点！上来上来！
Dahai! Come on! Come on!
干毬啥啊？
What  is this about?
去机场接焦老板，一人一袋白面
It's a gift from boss Jiao. A bag of flour per person.
走吧，快快快！
Come up here, come on.
那焦老板新买了个私人飞机，从香港回来了
Jiao has a new private jet. He's flying in from Hong Kong.
村里组织大家去迎接，去的一人一袋白面
We are the welcoming party. Everyone will receive a bag of flour.
飞机？地上放不下他了！买飞机？！
A plane? To live on this earth is not enough for him?
嗳，大海，昨天煤场开枪的时候，你在不在？
Dahai, say, were you at the coal mine when they started shooting?
在啊
I was.
到底是跑掉了什么人？
Who was the guy who ran?
煤矿的装卸工，四川的
A hauler from the coal field. From Sichuan.
他跑什么？十八湾的命案跟他有关系啦？
Why did he run? Weren't the murders in Shibawan?
那个后生也是个逃犯
He is an escaped prisoner.
在家乡杀了人了，跑这儿躲了两年多了
Killed someone in his hometown. He's wanted there.
警察来的时候，以为是抓他的
He thought he would be arrested.
吓得他撒腿就跑
The guy panicked and fled.
噢，逮住了没有？
And did they get him?
哝嗯，那能跑得了吗？！
Of course they did.
嗳，十八湾出事了啊 ?
What happened in Shibawan?
哎呀，你不知道？
Have not you heard?
昨天十八湾，有人用枪，打死三个后生
Someone killed three guys yesterday. Three died in Shibawan.
谁干的？
Says who?
不知道
I do not know.
今天清早，一车一车的武警
Earlier today, armed police were
都去了十八湾
em Shibawan.
哦，知道了，是这回事呀
Right. How tragic,
哦
right?
刘会计，嗳账算清楚了没有啊？
Accountant Liu. Your accounts are up to date?
嗳焦胜利当年承包村煤矿的时候说了
Listen. When the boss Jiao bought the coal mine ...
每年40%的红利给村委会
he said 40% of the profits would go to the village.
你给算算，这14年一共多少钱啊？
How much of the last 14 years of earnings he owes?
我和你说：2001年的时候
Listen. In 2001 ...
咱们村和县里已签了合同
village council signed
把煤矿卖给人家了
the sale of the coal mine.
那谁让你卖的呢？！
Who asked you to sell?
那经过村民委员会讨论了么？
Was the contract discussed?
那得讲诚信的呀！
We had to keep our word.
那焦胜利一铲子几十万，一铲子几十万
But Jiao is so rich
弄了一飞机？！
that he even bought a plane.
那是勤奋，人家！
That's not fair.
那你跟我说说，会计
He works hard.
你跟村长，你们俩受了多少贿啦？
How much did you get in bribes?.
都受贿了啊！
How much? Tell me, how much?
哎，师傅，停下！
Hey, come on, please.
噢，你跟我说说你受了多少贿啊？
How much did you take in bribes?
开门！
Open the door.
你们这些小官呀，比村长、焦胜利还坏！
People like you, are more miserable ...and diabolical than the village boss and Jiao.
跟我说说，你听我……
Just listen ... They ...
别碰我，不听
Do not talk to me.
大家，跟我再来上一遍啊
Repeat all.
欢迎！欢迎！热烈欢迎！
Welcome. Welcome!
Warm greetings!
好！
Great.
飞机来嘹！
The plane's coming.
欢迎！欢迎！热烈欢迎！
Welcome. Welcome!
Warm greetings!
董事长，你这又上一个台阶
Mr. Jiao, you have reached a new level.
一起进步哇
Let's move forward together.
啊哈哈哈哈
嫂子，恭喜了
Congratulations, lady.
小鬼，献花
Children,  the flowers.
欢迎！欢迎！热烈欢迎！
Welcome. Welcome!
Warm greetings!
来，焦总，看这里。哎，好的
Mr. Jiao, look here.
哎，好 [看这儿]
哎，挨着近一点，好，嗳，好
Closer. This.
董事长说几句吧？
Say something, sir.
一会儿吧，啊
Later.
唻，请！
Let's go.
啊，是井泉啊，呵呵
How are you, Aunt?
啊，不错啊
Thanks for coming.
哦，好久不见，哦呵呵
Wow, it's been awhile!.
胜利！
Shengli!
哎哟，大海！
Dahai.
嗳，胜利，祝贺祝贺！
Shengli. Congratulations!
谢谢啊，大海，啊
Thanks, Dahai.
嗳，好不容易见到焦董事长
You're a hard man to reach.
我给你说个事吧
I have a topic you'd like to discuss with you.
能不能赞助俺一下啊？
I need a favor.
有什么需要，你就说吧
Whatever you need, just ask.
赞助俺俩钱
Sponsor my trip to Beijing.
买火车票去北京，告你和村长的状！
To bring charges against you and the village chief.
行啊，过俩天，我去安排
I know. Come talk to me later.
哎，你能不能当着全村人的面
No, here in front of everybody.
说一说村里的经济问题？
Can you not discuss the economy of the village?
你瞪我作甚啊？！
What are you are looking at?!
㖿！
呃！㖿！
嗬，嗬，嗬，嗬
小白，你那是打高尔夫了啊！
Xiao Bai, you play golf?
喂，啊，呃，咳，咳，嗯，嘒
我代表胜利集团来慰问你啊
I'm here to apologize on behalf of Shengli group.
就这样吧
Case closed.
[读英语声]
你妈呢？
Where's your mother?
你是谁啊？
Who are you?
不记得我了？
Do not you remember me?
乌金山的胡舅舅
I'm your uncle, from Black Gold Mountain.
啊，俺妈打饭去了，一会儿就回来了
Mama went out to look for food. She'll be back soon.
Animal
"Animal".
牲口
Animal.
你爸呢 ?
And where is your father?
我爸呀，打animal（牲口）呢
Out hunting ... "animals".
去哪一个mountain（山头）？
On which mountain?
交口
Jiaokou.
呀，大海
Dahai.
姐呀
这是……
But what ...
甚候下来的啊？
What are you doing here?
这两天都在城里
I'm going to stay in the city for a couple days.
进屋喝杯茶吧
Feel free, then.
嗯
阿刚，先吃饭吧，吃了饭再写作业
Ganggang, eat first, then do the school work.
哦，知道了，妈
Okay, mother.
你，你这是？……
But what ...
说话呀
They told me...
嗐，前一段给你介绍个旺村的女的
Years ago I introduced you to a woman Wangchun.
人家条件挺好的
You were a beautiful couple.
你也是嘞
跟你约好了，你也不来
But you ... Why did you not want to go out with her?
嗐，自己的事情，一点儿也不操心
You never thought of yourself.
嗐，成天呀就是告状咯
And now you are making accusations.
你就是把人家告倒了，你也老了
Even if you keep right on talking, you will get old.
我是老了，不求所谓了
I am old. I do not care.
发烧了么！
Do not be silly.
这才过了半辈子就老了？
You are in middle age.
我娃在呢……
The kids are home.
妳骂俺吧！
I miss you.
你就是不成器
You're still immature.
上学那会儿，我就说你了
I told you when we were in school.
不要净想着发财
There's more to life than getting rich.
你能比上人家焦胜利万恶了？
You want to be worse than Jiao Shengli?
噫！妳也拿他跟我比呀？！
What? How can you compare me to him?
不跟人家比跟谁比咯？
If not him, then who?
你说咱们都是同学
You and he were classmates.
瞧人家过的那是什么日子呢，你看看咱们
Look at what he has become. Compared with us here.
那你哇，在乌金山上还有一间房子
You have your house in Wujinshan.
我和你姐夫呢
But my husband and I
到现在呢，我们还租房养子呢
have a house that is ours.
嗐，不要想那些了
Enough complaining.
你要是有时间，还不如开个小饭店
If you have time and money, open a restaurant or a store.
或是弄个商店，挣了些钱，娶个媳妇
To make money and get married.
日子是自己的，管毬他们做什么呢！
Your life belongs to you. Stop worrying about what others do.
姐，妳看着吧
My dear, wait and see.
要比万恶，我比村长和焦胜利他们还万恶！
You bet I'll be worse than the village head or Jiao.
[广播音]
……其中，以技改为核、内外型投资
涨42.5%，增幅高出全市……
老“高”回来了！
Mr. Golf?
你叫我什么？
What did you call me?
老“高”嘛
Mr. Golf.
现在大家都叫你老“高”——高尔夫
That's what they're calling you.
你不知道？
Did you not know?
老“高”！
Mr. Golf.
[晋剧《林冲夜奔》]
俺
I...
林冲
Lin Chong...
一时忿怒
I grabbed my sword in anger ...
拔剑杀死
and beheaded two
高俅奸细二贼
henchmen Gao Giu.
多蒙柴大官人
Fortunately for me, the official Chai ...
赠俺书信一封
gave me a document that prevents me ...
荐往梁山去嗻
from going to Mount Liang.
那贼头畜牲
为雪此恨亮山刀
[虎啸声]
[背景音：晋剧《铡判官》]
大海
Dahai.
嫂子
Good day.
大海，来了
Dahai, good day
俺跟会计商量点事情
I want to talk to your husband.
你们说吧
Feel free.
写吧
Write.
啥呐？
Write what?
村长这些年贪污多少，你最清楚
You know how much the village chief pocketed.
你给俺写个口供
Make a confession.
你瞎说啥哪你？
You're being ridiculous.
哎！
做啥你这叫？
What are you doing?
那危险啊！
This is dangerous.
你给我写！
Write.
写啊！
Write it!
写呀！
Write.
[警笛声]
哼哼
你打啊！
Shoot!
你朝我这儿打！
Come on, shoot!
你这㞞样，玩把枪呢你还
You are too cowardly to kill me!
咋的了？！
Dahai!
喂？
Hello?
村长，我是刘镏
Village boss. It Liuliu.
刚到村委会
I just got here.
啊，请指示
What do you want me to do?
啊，行啦，你放心吧，下午就办
Do not worry. I'll do it this afternoon.
老“高”
Mr. Golf.
村长呢？
Where's the boss?
去庙里了
He's in the temple.
你刚才叫我甚呢？
What did you call me?
老“高”呀
Mr. Golf.
你不是猥样就像个“高尔夫”嘛
Isn't that your foreign name?
贱货
Asshole.
说啥呢你呀？
What did you say?
[广播音]
国务院8月7号正式批复
我省国家资源及经济、环境……
……改革总体方案
总体方案指明了资源型经济转型的方向……
大海！
Dahai!
你做甚啊？
What is it?
去奉节那面。怎么呢？打什么呢？
Where are you going? Are you going hunting?
嗯，打牲口
Yes. Hunting animals.
……邀请专家分析总体方案
破解山西经济发展的三大问题
我省是典型的资源型地区
长期以来为国家能源供应和现代化建设
做出了突出贡献
但由于过份依赖……
唔
大海
Dahai.
这可不是闹着耍的
Do not do anything stupid.
冷静点
Calm down.
咱们有啥话不能坐下来说？
Let's sit down and talk.
非要这的了
And solve this issue.
听我的
Listen, Dahai,
不要冲动
do not be impulsive.
咱们坐下来说……
Let sit ...
……环境恶化
资源浪费严重
等一系列矛盾和问题
亟需通过深化改革和鼓励机制创新……
驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾、驾……
贱货！
Idiot.
大海？
Dahai?
有啥要求
How can we take care of it?
你就说吧
Let's just talk.
哎，师傅，师傅
Hey mister.
嗳，借个火
Mister, you got a light?
没有
No.
摩的！摩的！摩的！
Motorcycle taxi! Motorcycle taxi!
兄弟，要不要摩的？
Hey man, where are you going?
高速路口
Take the expressway.
是重庆还是武昌方向呀？
Towards Chongging or Wushan?
重庆
Chongging.
来，走啊
Let's go.
我们的周妈妈含辛茹苦地把儿女们拉扯大
Our dear Ms. Zhou worked hard to raise their children.
在她七十大寿之际
And now,as she turns 70, we wish her ...
我们祝贺她：福如东海，健康长寿！
happiness, good health and long life.
下面，我们请老人家的二儿子一家
And now, let's welcome the second son and his family.
给老人家拜寿！
And his good wishes.
三娃回来啰！
All her children are here!
哦，小儿子回来了？
The younger son has returned!
三儿回来啰！
You're back ...
仨，回来啦
大哥！
Brother ...
刚刚到
嗯
[女演员刘陆，出演《一步之遥》]
嗳！
你跑嘛你跑？回去
Why are you running away? Come here.
过去！啧！
Come here.
妈……
Mother
别哭啦！
Do not cry.
你从哪里回来的？
How did you come?
俺是走的水路
I came by boat.
之前呢？
And before that?
收到过你两笔钱，一共13万
I received the money you sent. 130,000 yuan.
那就对了撒
That's right.
最后一笔，是从山西寄的
The latest shipment was from Shanxi.
[叹息声]
武汉做的，山西寄的
I earned it in Wuhan and sent it from Shanxi.
我不要你的钱
I do not want your money.
大哥二哥来了
Your brothers are coming.
仨
- 大哥
- 嗳
二哥
- 弟妹呢？
- 里屋呢
坐！坐！
妈的生日，本来是十一月初七，这个你晓得的
Mom's birthday was on November 7th.
但是，我跟你二哥，在外头打工，回来不到
But we both had to work all day. We could not go home.
村上的这个亲戚，在外头打工，也回来不到
Our relatives were also unable to go home.
就想着今天三十，人多
And now that it's New Year's and many people ...
嗳，所以就改在今天办
go home, we decided to celebrate today.
我，还是跟你们两个交代一下，啊
I'll be honest with you.
妈这回过七十大寿
To commemorate 70 years of the mother,
我们总共收礼金
we received gifts ...
收了：1万零270块钱
Cash totaling 10,270 yuan.
嗯
办了12桌
买肉、买菜、买酒、买烟
To buy meat, vegetables, wine and cigarettes the total cost ...
总共花了6477块3角3
was 6,477 yuan and 33 cents.
嗨
还请了个礼仪，花了8百块钱
I hired a host for 800 yuan.
再加上些零零星星七七八八的
Taking into account all expenses ...
统共就花了7485块4角2
the total expenditure was 7,485 yuan and 42 cents.
统共就花这么多钱
That was the total cost.
嗳
那就还剩到2784块5角8
Which leaves us with two thousand 784 yuan and 58 cents.
那钱呢，我是这么想的
This money, in my opinion, should be divided between ...
我们兄弟三个，加上妈妈一个
the three of us and Mom.
一人一份，做四份，分下去
One fourth for everyone.
这钱都分好了
I already divided it for us. Into four equal parts.
嗳
他二叔，是这么料吧？
Okay. Second brother?
对头，对头
Okay. Right.
我那份不要，你给妈妈
I do not need the money. Give my part to mother.
哼，嗯
办事情还买了一条娇子烟，就剩那么多
I brought 10 packs of cigarettes. Good brand.
呵，还有九根
Nine are missing.
那么，一个人三根，分了
So there are 3 for each.
大哥做事情，从来都是，一碗水端平
As elder brother I have to be impartial.
啊
Soon.
你那份，要孝敬妈
If you want to give your part to Mom,
你个人给她
give it to her yourself.
别人都是大年初一才拜神咧
People usually worship the gods in the morning.
我这是在拜鬼
I am worshipping ghosts.
你们要怪，就怪老天爷
The gods are for blaming.
有啥子想不通，就去问他
If you have any sorrows, tell the heavens about them.
琴琴不是在东莞吗？没和你们一起回来？
Quinqin is in Dongguan? She returned to you?
她今年在中山干着
She was sent to Zhongshan.
回不来喽
She will not return.
在中山查出艾滋病啰
The tested HIV positive.
艾滋病？
She has AIDS?
她原来不是在台湾厂里干吗？
Didn't she work in the factory?
哎呀，那破地方谁吃得消！
Yes. It's impossible to make a decent living.
芳子和那丽丽在中山干发廊，琴琴就过去了嘚
Lili has a hairdressing salon in Zhongshan ... Quinqin went to work for her.
后来又到大宾馆去干特殊服务，得的艾滋病
She provided "special services" there. That's how she got AIDS.
黄毛
Blonde.
你不是和她打过炮嘛
You slept with her once.
赶紧验一验，有没有传染上哦
You better get a check-up.
你说啥子啊？莫东说西说的啊！
Do not talk nonsense!
赶紧验一验，莫中镖哦
A quick check-up can't hurt. I wish you good luck.
你婆娘在天津干啥子？
What your wife doing up in Tianjin ...
你在这个村子晓不晓得呢？
while you're stuck here? You should keep an eye on her.
我看你赶紧回去
You should keep an eye on her.
把她带到医院里验一验啊
Maybe you have HIV.
莫把女儿传染去了
你说啥子？
Come on, man!
我说你干嘛说别人闲话？
You should keep your mouth shut.
小子你想死啊！
Want to die?
你来，老子让你过不到年！
Son of a bitch. We'll sort it out here and now.
𡂿，锤子，快点快点！要动手就赶快！
Going to fight?
离新年敲钟时间还有1小时零18分喽！
It's only 78 minutes until the New Yearr.
小子，来，看我啥子喇？看我
Think you can take me?
老爸给你放个炮
Should we light some fireworks?
好
Cool!
看好啦
Look!
嗯
广州，两百四，两百四
Tickets to Guangzhou, 240 yuan.
武汉要不要？要不要？要不要？
Wuhan! Anyone for Wuhan?
武汉武汉，要不要？
要不要票？
Want a ticket?
有没有去南宁的？
Do have any for Nanning?
有，要几张票么？
Yes, how many do you want?
还有去哪的？
For where else?
有……宜昌的
Yichang.
广州、宜昌、南宁各要一张
One to Guangzhou, Nanning and Yichang.
那你在桥口头等等我嘛，我好给你拿去啦
Wait for me at the bridge, pick up the tickets there.
快点撒
Don't take long.
好，你等着哈
Wait for me.
各位旅客，你们好
Ladies and gentlemen,
重庆火车站提醒您
the Chonqqing railway station... reminds everyone ...
春运期间严禁携带
that during the holiday season ...
易燃、易爆
it is strictly prohibited carrying combustible materials ...
枪支、管制刀具等危险物品
你到底是去广州
Are you going to Guangzhou
还是宜昌？
Yichang...
还是南宁？
or Nanning?
妳翻我的包包啦？
You went through my things?
我看情况吧，我想去缅甸
I'm not sure. I would go to Burma.
就在村子里头呆着，不出去不行呐？
You can't stay here in the village?
没意思
It is boring.
什么叫没意思？
What is boring?
枪响的那一下子有意思
Shooting is not boring.
你去缅甸做啥子吗？
And what would you do in Burma?
我去那边换把快枪
I need to buy a new gun.
那你买个手机，我好找得到你撒
You should buy a cellphone. So I could call you.
不大行
No way,
太危险了
it's very dangerous.
想啥子买点？
Can I help you?
嗳，我看一下
I'm just looking.
你请随便看
Take your time.
阿姐，厕所在哪里？
Where is the bathroom?
那边嗫
Right there.
妳帮我看下包包，我回来再看
Can you watch my backpack? I'll be right back.
要得，你去嘛
Okay. I look after it.
你先去把车开过来嘛
Go ahead and start the car.
妳注意到点哈
Be careful.
嗯，晓得
You can leave.
小燕
Xiaoyan!
上哪儿去啊？
Where are you going?
去给孩子打疫苗
I'm taking him for a vaccination. It's time for the injection.
乖乖，要打针针了啊
But how cute!
怕不怕啊？
Is he scared?
说“不怕”
No.
最近忙不忙？
And the rest?
还行，还是老样子
As usual.
改天喝茶哈
Let's have tea sometime.
再见啊！
Sure.
嗳，拜拜！
干嘛去？
啊！
[背景音：杜琪峰导演的电影《放逐》]
哎，师傅，停下车
Hey, driver, here.
哎，停车
Hey, stop!
下个服务区才能停
I can't, only on the next rest stop.
就这儿！下车！
Here!
堵车了吗？
Did you take transit?
过天门的时候堵了一会儿
A delay in Tianmen.
妳什么时候到的？
When did you get here?
我刚到
I just got in.
又皱眉头
You're frowning.
嗯嗯……
一会儿怎么走？
Should we go to to the station?
我叫了黑车，给司机打电话他就过来
I rented a car. The driver is waiting.
喂？王师傅，是我
Hello? Wang? It's me.
刚才租车的小玉
Car rented by Xiaoyu.
你把车开过来吧
You can come now.
好
Right.
你跟她说了吗？
You told her?
说了一点
I started to.
怎么说的？
What did you say?
没说通
I left it implicit.
你就拖吧
You're stalling again.
她应该明白了
She must have understood.
跟我回广州吧
Come with me to Guangzhou.
我跟了你这么多年，我等什么？
I've been with you for many years. And what have I got?
我不给我自己一个交代
I accepted things the way they were.
我还得给我爸妈一个交代
But I owe my parents an explanation.
我想要个孩子
I want a child.
一起回广州吧
Let's go together to Guangzhou.
要么你和她好好过，咱俩分开
Either you stay with your wife, and we get separated ...
要么你离，我们好好过
or you leave her and live with me.
不能再拖了
You have to choose.
一起走吧
Let's stay together.
你回广州
So you go back to Guangzhou,
我给你半年的时间
and I give you 6 months.
咱俩好好想想，做个了断吧
We need to think it over before we make a decision.
哎，那个同志，你这个包包有点问题
Sir, there's a problem with your luggage.
麻烦你过来检查一下
Please, come this way.
把包打开
Open your luggage.
这个不能带上车
You can not take that on the train.
那是水果刀
It's a fruit knife.
水果刀还是不能带
It is not allowed.
咋不能带？
Why not?
有规定不能带
It's the law.
那我吃苹果怎么办？
And if I want to eat an apple?
连皮一起吃啊
Eat with the skin.
给我喽，我带回去
Give it to me, then. I'll take it.
那妳不上车啊？
You can not go.
我不上
I'm not going.
那妳也不能进站哪
Or enter the station.
刀我不要了
Stay with the knife.
身份证拿出来
Your ID?
我就先走了
I'll leave first.
到了，给我打个电话
Call me when you get there.
呐，给你
Here, you can go.
各位旅客，你们好！
Hello.
由宜昌东开往广州东的快速934次列车
This is the final call for the 9:34 train from Yichang to Guangzhou.
已经请旅客们上车了
野三关的各位父老乡亲
Dear citizens of Yuanshan, come take a look.
请走过来，看过来！
Come and see.
看一看！ 瞧一瞧！
看灵蛇，看美女！
See the sacred snakes. See their beauty.
姻缘天注定！
Marriage is the destination.
灵蛇知祸福！
The sacred snakes predict happiness and distress.
看一看！ 瞧一瞧！
Come and see. Come and see.
看灵蛇，看美女！
See the sacred snakes. See their beauty.
姻缘天注定！
灵蛇知祸福！
看一看！ 瞧一瞧！
看灵蛇，看美女！
姻缘天注定！
灵蛇知祸福！
看一看！ 瞧一瞧！
[宾馆霓虹灯招牌：夜归人]
看灵蛇，看美女！
[背景音：电视剧《新白娘子传奇》]
敢问相公是本地人士吗？
我姓许，名仙，字汉文
我们家小姐是问你：可是本地人士？
先生，您好！住宿还是桑拿？
Good evening, sir. Overnight or sauna?
妳是叫小玉吧？
Are you Xiayou?
是啊
I am.
我是张亚贤的老婆
I am Zhang, Youllang's wife.
啊！干嘛！
Why?!
骚货！
Shameless bitch. I'll kill you!
- 唔！肏！
- 啊！
嘿！𡂿！㗼！
妳个臭不要脸的骚货！啊！
打的就是妳！我跟妳讲！啊！
妳的爸妈把妳生下来
Your mother gave birth to you
是让妳勾引别人老公的吗？！啊！
just to seduce my husband?
上钟了！上钟了！11号
Number 11, your turn.
[背景音：徐克导演的电影《青蛇》]
哼，一会抓苍蝇，一会爬房梁
不是上窜就是下跳的
你就不能安静地坐会儿？
那你那个老实人，在船上也瞎折……
谢谢！
Thank you.
不称赞
You're welcome.
妳在广州做了这些年
You were in there a long time.
好歹还有点儿积蓄噻
You should know how things are.
妳要不到广州做
Around here,
苦命哪里挣到钱？
I don't have much to do to make money.
不想出去了
I'd rather stay here.
这机场啥时候能修好呢？
When will this airport will be ready?
也要等，是修跑道的
They are working on the railroad first.
那个跑道修齐了，工人就要撤了
When this is over, most workers will leave.
妳妈也要走啦
I will, too.
妈……
Mother ..
我在宜昌看到我爸了
I saw father in Yichang.
他的事啊，妳再不说了啊
I don't want to know anything about him.
重点工程建设
作为我省扩大投资的重要抓手
今年上半年整期重点工程
完成投资625.8亿元
同比增长37.6%
拉动全社会投资增长11个百分点
带动全省全社会
固定资产投资额完成1905亿元
推动三次……
我靠！这可是怎么了？！
Amazing! How did this happen?
昨晚八点三十八分
Yesterday at 8:38,
北京至福州的动301次列车
the train from Beijing to Fuzhou ...
行驶至温州双屿路段时
via Shuanguy and Wenzhou ...
与前方一停驶的杭州前往福州的
crashed into a train that was stopped en route from Hengzhou to Fuzhou.
动3115次列车追尾
造成动301次列车的第一到第四节车厢脱线
The collision made the first 4 cars plummet from the viaduct.
从高架桥上掉落
动3115次列车的两节车厢脱线
Two cars of another train also fell.
截至目前，事故已经造成35人遇难
At the moment, the death toll comes to 35.
其中19人身份已确认
包括两名外籍人士
Among them are two foreigners.
另有210人受伤
In total, 210 people were injured.
收费
Pay the fee.
收啥子费？
What rate?
收10块钱的过行费
To pass through, 10 yuan.
我们是机场工地的
We work on the site.
我就是要收你们机场工地的过行费！
Then you will understand.
你们机场工地的大卡车从我们乡镇泥路上过
When your trucks pass through our city,
弄得大坑小坑的，从今天起，正式收费！
they leave holes. As of today will have to pay a fee.
我开的又不是大卡车
But I'm just an employee.
不是大卡车就不收费了啊？！
It makes no difference.
[演员王宏伟：电影《小武》、《站台》的主演]
你是不是机场工地的呀？
You work at the airport?
有发票没嘚？有发票我就交！
I'll pay if you give me a receipt.
发票？……
A receipt?
发票
Come here.
收拾收拾他呀！
Give the receipt to him.
呃啾！
呃！呃！
啊！呃啾！
哎，就给！就给！
哎，没事了！没事了！
再打！
哎，不要打啦！不要打啦！
别打啦！别打啦！打死人啦！
Stop or you'll kill him.
[背景音：
CCTV科教频道节目《自然传奇》]
动物也会自杀吗？
An animal commits suicide?
这一言论，大概对于那些认为
For those who think that humans ...
人类是地球唯一高级生命的人来说
are the only advanced creatures on earth ...
肯定是无法接受的
嗳，小玉，妳该下班啦
Xiaoyu, your shift is over.
人类总认为自己……
妳晓不晓得动物也会自杀？
Did you know that animals commit suicide?
嗐！要不怎么说是动物呢？
They don't know what they're talking about.
对我来说呢，好死不如赖活着！
Better to live miserable than die happy.
呵呵，动物可不会那么想
The animals do not agree.
近些年
由于社会压力诱发之下
越来越多的人选择自杀
但事实证明
自杀不仅是人类的特权……
先生您好！欢迎光临！
Good evening, gentlemen.
有些动物……
Sauna or spend the night?
请问您是桑拿还是住宿？
……甚至集体自杀……
先桑拿，后住宿
Sauna, and then give us a room.
请！
桑拿，桑拿，两位桑拿，两位桑拿
Sauna. Two patrons to the sauna.
妹子，洗衣服啊？
Washing clothes?
是的
Yes.
妳是几号？
What is your number here?
我没嘚号
I have no number.
妳给我按吧
Give me a massage.
我不会按，请到三楼
Please go to the third floor.
按摩的都在楼上呢
The masseuses are there.
就是要不会按的
I do not want a professional.
这样，给我做全套，给妳小费撒
Give me a full body massage. I paid.
对不起，先生，我是前台的，我不是做按摩的
Sorry, sir, I'm the receptionist, I am not masseuse.
前台？那么妳在包间里面？
Receptionist? Then why are you up here?
呵，对不起
Excuse me.
妳么意思撒？
What are you implying?
我没啥子意思
Nothing.
莫看不起人啊
Do not turn your back on me.
少不了妳的钱
You will be well rewarded.
出去！
Fuck you!
你妈！你装什么装！
Damn! Stop pretending!
老子今天点妳了！
I'll have you.
我不是做按摩的！
I'm not a masseur.
妳不是做按摩的，在桑拿干嘛？
Then why are you working in a sauna?
出去！
Out!
我肏！
Damn!
小白脸玩多了，嫌我丑是吧？
You only get with beautiful men, huh?
怕我没嘚钱啊？
We have money to pay you.
我不是小姐！回家找你老婆去！
I'm not a prostitute. Go home to your wives.
你干嘛？
What do you want now?
老子今天要办妳！
I'll have you.
我就是不做！
No you will not.
不做？！
I will.
老子有钱！
I have money.
有钱啥了不起？！
Money can not buy everything.
老子就是有钱！
I have money.
有钱也不行啊？！嗯？！
It is not good enough is it?
有钱也不行啊？！
Not good enough?
妈的老子有钱不行？！
有钱也不行啊？！
妈的老子有钱！
My money is not good enough, is it? Bitch.
老子用钱砸死妳！
我砸死妳！
妳不是小姐？！
You're not a prostitute, are you? I know you'll do anything for money.
老子用钱砸死妳！
You're like all the others, doing it for money.
我砸死妳！我砸死妳！我砸死妳！
你妈！
Bitch! Bitch! I have money!
老子有钱！
老子有钱也不行啊？！
My money is good.
嗯？！
你妈！
Bitch!
肏你！
Go fuck yourself!
老子就是有钱！
My money is not good, is it? Bitch! My money is good, yes.
老子有钱也不行？！老子有钱也不行？！
嗯？！嗯？！
你妈！肏你妈！
Bitch, you will learn a lesson.
妳不是小姐，谁是小姐？！
You are not a prostitute? Is that so?
妳不是小姐？！妳不是小姐？！
妳不是小姐？！妳不？！
Bitch. You're a slut.
肏你！
老子有钱！
You are.. Take this to learn.
妳不是小姐？！嗯？！
嗯！
老子砸死妳！
His ...
啊！ [嚯！]
你妈！……
Bitch!
啊！ [噗！]
啊！
你好！这里是110报警中心，请讲
Hello, You have reached the police. What do you want?
我杀人了
I killed someone.
别碰老子手机
Hands off my mobile.
GPS在哪呢？
And where's the GPS?
日你妈！你买宝马了？要用GPS
If you want a GPS, buy a fucking BMW.
老子去东莞找老乡，定定位，看怎么走
I'm going to see a friend in Dongguan.
能怎么走？
I do not know the way.
出门坐摩的
Call a motorcycle taxi.
然后坐摩的去火车站呗
Then take a train.
是动车好不好？
A high speed train?
东莞有七八个镇呢，你去哪个镇？
Which town in Dongguan?
虎门
Humen.
虎门？
Humen?
啊！
啊？！不该的！
Help me.
你说怎么办吧？
What should I do?
公司有规定：“上班时间不许串岗”，唔？
The rule of the company is clear:No chat during office hours.
今天的事故，主要责任在你呀！
Today's accident was your fault.
对不对？
Agree or not?
医药费这些，公司出
The company will pay for medical treatment.
误工费你出吧
You will pay by the hour for his work.
常岭的手，估计十天半个月好不了
It will take two weeks to get his hand healed.
这段时间，你的工资归他
During this period his salary goes to him.
你替他打工
You work for him.
女士们，先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
列车前方停车站是：东莞车站
our next stop is Dongguan.
[粤语]
女士们，先生们
Ladies and gentlemen,
[粤语]
列车前方停车站是：东莞车站
our next stop is Dongguan.
嘿，老友！
Hey, man. What's up?
喂，你好！
- 乌拉！
- 嗨！
Hi.
他休息一天，我就要包他一天的工资唻
While he is on leave, he gets my salary.
他休息一百天，我就要包他一百天的工资
If he is out 100 days, I go 100 days without pay.
肏你妈妈去！
What the hell!
这不是你帮他打工啊？！
This means that you work for him.
所以老子就跑的了！
So I left.
还好老子刚发的工资，老子不亏
Fortunately I had got paid a few days earlier.
肏，那我跟你说
So you have some money..
现在我们厂正招人
Come work here. Companies are hiring.
底薪一千二，包吃住
Basically they pay 1,200 yuan, plus room and board.
一般多钱呢？
How much do people usually get?
一般两千五
Nearly 2,500 yuan.
要培训吧？
Training?
培训一个星期，没工资拿
A week without pay.
还有别的工作吗？
Anything in particular?
到常平去干服务员，你搞不搞？
You could work as a waiter in Changping.
端盘子啰？
Waiter?
夜总会，来的全是港鼠和台巴子
It's a nightclub. The owners are from Hong Kong and Taiwan.
喜欢给小费，就是要熬夜值班
The tips are good, but you would have to work all night.
常平远不？
It is near here?
不远，也是东莞的一个镇啊
No, it's in another town in Dongguan.
你好！刘生
Hello, Mr. Lau
刘生啊，这个是我老乡，请多多关照一下
This guy is from my village. Please, take care of him.
这就是你的兄弟啊？
Your buddy?
对，叫小辉
Yes, his name is Xiaohui.
小辉，上车
Xiaohui, come in.
小辉啊，有事打我电话啦
Call me if anything happens.
没什么事啦
Nothing will happen.
好好
Take care of him.
刘生，拜托拜托！
I will.
好啦！
客人来的时候，不要再称呼为“先生”了
When a guest arrives, do not call him "sir."
从今天开始
As of now
应当尊称为贵宾
he is the "distinguished guest".
要说：
You say,
“贵宾你好！欢迎光临！”
"Good evening, distinguished guest, welcome to the Golden Age. "
跟我说一遍
Now repeat what I say:
贵宾你好！
Good evening, distinguished guest.
欢迎光临盛世中华娱乐城！
welcome to the Golden Age
广东话
Now in Cantonese.
[粤语]
贵宾你好！
欢迎光临盛世中华娱乐城！
英文
In English.
Dear guests, welcome to the Golden Age!
带客人到214房间
Take the guest to room 214
啧，你怎么进来的啊？
What are you doing?
我没看到！
I didn't see anything.
你没看到嘛啊？
What you did not see?
我——什么都没看到！
Nothing.
行啦，我已经好啦
It's okay, I'm not naked.
新来的啊？
You're the newbie?
嗯
Yeah.
叫什么？
Your name?
小辉
Xiaohui.
湖南的啊？
From Hunan?
妳如是晓得啊？
How did you know?
那当然撒，你一讲话我就晓得
Easy. By your accent.
我也是湖南的啰
I am also from Hunan.
过来
Help me out here.
我叫莲蓉
I'm Lianrong.
莲蓉月饼的莲蓉
It means "lotus seed".
好记吧？
Easy to remember.
嗯，好吃
Delightful.
[跺靴声]
咱俩还挺有缘的哈
Fate brought us together here.
切
这地方人来人往的，有缘的人多着呢
Fate brings a lot of people together here.
帮我弄一下呗
Help me with the tie?
啊
«Вперёд, заре навстречу!»
[前苏联歌曲《向前，迎接黎明！》]
(«Молодая гвардия - гимном комсомола»)
[又名《青年近卫军：共青团之歌》]
«Das Andreas Hofer Lied»
[改编自德国民歌《安德烈亚斯•霍费尔之歌》]
[莞式服务：制服诱惑~红粉军阵]
老板
Sir ...
喂？
Hello?
我在东莞呢
I'm in Dongguan.
徐悲鸿的啊？
A painting by Xu Beihong?
拿下
Buy.
哎呀，那可宝着呢
It's a great investment.
行了，那就澳门见了
Okay, see you in Macau. Hanging up.
就这样
[本片导演：贾樟柯]
嗳，你偷懒
Slacking off?
没有没有
No.
妳也偷懒
And you? Are you slacking off?
这房间Wi-Fi太好了！
The Wi-Fi is good in this room.
晚上客人多吗？
Do they have many guests?
不好说
I'll explain.
凌晨一点一拨，三点一拨
One shift arrives at one in the morning. The other  at three.
五点钟还有一拨呢
And another at five.
哇！山西、内蒙都下雪了
It's snowing in Shangi and Mongolia.
不会吧？东莞二十四度呢
No way. It's 24 degrees here in Dongguan.
我靠！
Shit!
东北一个土地局局长
The minister of the city
家里搜出130多个LV包
bought almost 130 bags of Louis Vitton.
他要那么多包干什么？
Why did he buy so much?
她是个女的啊
It is actually a she.
女的就要那么多包？
A woman needs all that?
所以说她是个女的嘛
Like I said, she is a lady.
跟个帖
I'll post a comment.
写什么？
What should I write?
TMD！——他妈的！
Fuck that.
他妈的！
Fuck that!
至少得两百多万呢！
The bags are worth more than 2 million yuan.
还有什么呀？
Anything else?
山西煤矿爆炸
A mine exploded in Shanxi.
死了十几个人呢
Dozens killed.
跟个帖
Post a comment.
说什么？
Post what?
TMD！
Fuck that.
他妈的！啧
Fuck that!
哎，你有网名吗？
What's your username?
QQ：我是一只小小鸟
Well my handle is Little Bird.
真的很小吗？
Is it little?
哎，妳干么子啊？这样粗鲁！
Hey now you've gone too far! Stop.
哎哟，做好事唻
Just a hand!
还怕羞
You were embarrassed.
妳的网名呢？
And what is your username?
哎呀！
Wow!
你帮我看着
I forgot!
没死吧？
They're not dead.
妳养鱼啊？
You keep fish?
我明天要去放生
I will release them tomorrow.
妳信佛？
Are you Buddhist?
信啊
I am.
做咱们这行的，广东人叫“捞偏门”
In this kind of work the Cantonese call us illegal traders.
所以我们要多做善事，来生才能得到解脱
So we need to do many good deeds to be forgiven in our next life.
懂不懂啊？“小小鸟”
You got it ... Little Bird?
我的网名叫“寻水的鱼”
My handle is Fish Seeks Water.
[莞式服务：泳装情挑~仕女怀春]
欢迎光临盛世中华娱乐城！
I'm here. Distinguished guest, welcome to the Golden Age
Dear guests, welcome to the Golden Age!
欢迎光临！7号房这边请，7号房这边
Welcome. The distinguished guests from room 7 have arrived.
啊，我们今天“开车学粤语”呢
Now for the 1st lesson of the series “Learn to speak Cantonese.”
就要教大家啊
在对的时间当中，遇上对的人的时候
When you find the ideal person ...
应该说一些什么样的粤语
You'll know what to say in Cantonese.
一般两个人刚刚开始有点感觉
When two people meet for the first time ...
男孩子够胆呢，就要跟女生说：“喜欢你！”
if the boy is brave enough he will say "I like you".
你要知道现在东莞呢，可是女比男多
In Dongguan, it is more common that...
女孩子讲给男孩子听的几率是非常高的啊哦！
the girls approach the boys ...
切！~
What?
我会说一句广东话
I only know one phrase in Cantonese.
你讲啊
Tell me.
我好钟意你！
I really like you.
咱们离开东莞吧！
Let's leave Dongguan.
你准备带我去哪里？
And where will you take me?
只要妳跟我走，哪都行
Anywhere works, as long as you come with me.
“欢场无真爱”
There is no real love in sex work.
你了解我吗？
Think you really know me?
我有一个女儿
I have a daughter.
你在车上遇见我的那天
That day you saw me on the train,
我是去广州看她
I was going to see her in Guangzhou.
她三岁了
She lives there.
我得养她
I have to get her.
你要去哪里？[粤语]
你要去邊度？
Where's yours?
急诊室，你呢？[粤语]
急診室，你呢？
The music room. And yours?
列车包厢那边 [粤语]
列車包廂嗰度.
In the train room.
进来
Come in.
我不要护士，我要列车员
I want a driver, not a nurse.
护士不是挺好的吗？
Would it not be better with a nurse?
您得为您的健康着想呀！
You need to consider your health.
好了好了
That's enough.
有病的同志更需要妳
Go look for sick customers.
可是……
But ...
我很健康
My health is excellent.
走人
You can go.
那您等着吧
Please, wait.
贵宾您好！这是您的果盘
Your fruit, distinguished guest.
放那
Let it there.
嗯
贵宾好！我可以为您服务吗？
Distinguished guest, can I help you?
应该叫“首长”
Take me to the conductor of the train
首长好！
That's me.
这还差不多，咱们发车吧
Very well. Let's get going.
想去哪儿？
Where?
想去哪儿，妳还不知道吗？
You do not know where we're going?
您想去哪儿就去哪儿呗
We can wherever you want to.
唉，现在的年轻人，连个方向都没有
You kids today have no sense of direction.
最近你们店里有什么创新啊？
Is that some recent innovation?
[左侧友情参演者：诗人韩东]
[莞式服务：制服诱惑~首长关爱]
这里，这里
Come here.
开心，兄弟
Relax, buddy.
我没别的地方去了，我就回来和你一起干
I have nowhere to go. I came here to join you.
那你就想清楚了
Think about it.
你不能说来就来，想走就走啰
If you stay,
到时候搞得兄弟我好没面子啊
do not fuck around, or I'll get scolded.
我晓得
I know.
你是新上线的吗？
Are you a newbie?
嗯，正在实习
Yes I'm in training.
你好！我是车间主管
Hi. Welcome, I'm your supervisor.
欢迎加入世界五百强企业！
Welcome to the Fortune 500.
好好干！
Work hard.
优秀员工公司招待台湾行
The best employees earn a trip to Taiwan ...
还可以参观公司总部哦
To visit our headquarters.
嗯
Okay.
加油！
Good luck.
你是哪里人啊？
Where are you from?
我湖南人，你呢？
Hunan. And you?
台湾
Taiwan.
嗯
喂，妈
Hi, Mom.
我这不是才把钱打给你了？
Did not send you money recently?
哦，我换工作了
I'm in a new job.
我们厂下月底才发钱
We get paid at the end of the month.
我才查的，没嘚钱
I really do not, I'm broke.
骗你干么子哇？
Why would I lie?
我现在就在银行门口，才出来的
I'm coming off the bench now. I don't have any money.
我不会乱花钱啵！
I'm not wasting.
我要吃要穿要住啊！
I can not live with nothing.
我又不是抢银行的！
I will not rob a bank.
我真的没乱花钱啊！
I did not waste the money.
你以为跑得过啊？
Did you really think you could escape?
常岭找你呢！
Chang Ling wants to see him.
胡云云？
Hu Yunyun?
到！
Here.
妳叫郑小玉？
Your name is Zheng Xiaoyu?
是
Yes.
妳的身份证
ID?
妳是湖北的？
You're from Hubei?
对
I am.
妳了解我们胜利集团吗？
Do you know anything about Shengli group?
在网上看过，知道一点儿
I searched the Internet. I know a little.
哦，这是焦太太，咱们公司现任董事长
This is Mrs. Jiao. She currently heads our company.
妳为什么这么远来山西找工作？
Why did you come so far to work here?
这儿有亲戚吗？
Do you have relatives here?
没有
No.
妳这要求太低了
A little older than the other suitors.
妳之前干过什么工作？
What kind of experience do you have?
我以前……
I worked
在广州的服装厂干过
in a garment factory in Guangzhou.
广州？
Guangzhou!
怎么现在不在广州干了？
Why did you leave Guangzhou?
我想换个环境
I wanted a new environment.
妳这名字好像在哪儿见过……
Your name is familiar.
妳在老家没事儿吧？
Are you running from some sort of problem?
没事儿了
No problem.
[晋剧《玉堂春》]
In court, the judge changed his mind.
He dishonored me, called me a killer ...
I could not defend myself.
I was forced to confess.
My tears fall.
Su san! Do you understand your sin?
苏三，你可知罪？！
你可知罪？！
Do you understand your sin?
人人生而有罪
活在大染缸中
人人猥琐旁观
人人凌弱欺善
人人互害相残
人人颟顸愚顽
……
恶业更重
罪孽更深
……
我有罪
我们有罪
……
忏悔吧